Guide to the Native American Educational Services David Beck Papers 1963-1991
University of Chicago Library
Native American Educational Services. David Beck. Papers
1936-2002
5.5 linear feet (11 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
David Beck served as a professor at NAES College in Chicago. This collection contains correspondence, syllabus, and administrative papers related to Beck's work at NAES. The collection forms part of the archives of Native American Educational Services.
Information on Use
Access
Series VII includes personnel material that is restricted until 2049.
Historical Note
Established in Chicago in 1974, NAES College (Native American Educational Service) aimed to improve the leadership of Native communities and to ensure that tribal knowledge, traditions and values play a major role in the higher education of Native students. Before closing its doors in 2007, NAES College offered a single degree, a Bachelor's of Arts in General Studies with an emphasis in Public Policy, and tribal knowledge, community service, community development and leadership.
Scope Note
The David Beck materials are organized by series. The largest portion of the collection is in the category Administrative Materials and consists of materials related to NAES. Within each category the materials are arranged in alphabetical order.
Series I: Correspondence contains correspondence to and from David Beck regarding NAES College.
Series II: Administrative Materials includes documents related to NAES such as registration and blank administrative forms.
Series III: Course Preparation Material contains Beck’s research materials for his courses in addition to course proposals and syllabus for courses.
Series VI: Materials related to Conferences, Meetings, and Festivals contains preparation materials for gatherings in addition to materials handed out at the conferences.
Series V: A bibliographic material contains library printouts, reading lists and bibliographies.
Series VI: Essays include reprints by other scholars on subjects of community leadership.
Series VII: Grants materials include budgets, grant applications in addition to letters of congratulations and rejection.
Series VIII: A restricted material includes files for which access is restricted. Evaluations and recommendations have been restricted in compliance with University of Chicago policies.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Beck, David; NAES College; Indians of North America; Indians of North America -- Education (Higher); Indian universities and colleges -- United States
INVENTORY
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Americans for Indian Opportunity, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Canadian Consulate, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Campus Correspondence, before August 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Campus Correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Faith Hill, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chicago campus, 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fort Peck, 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Menominee, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - North Central Association, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, registrar, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Terry Strauss, letters and resumes, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Twin Cities, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Administrative Materials
  - Admission application, blank, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Therese Alston, Clark Atlantic Catalog, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Americans for Indian Opportunity survey, 1977-2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Admission Applications, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - David Beck’s resumes, 1994-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Brochures/flyers for NAES, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - CAIEC, Education, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Calendars, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Census, disc, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chicago Forum, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chicago Public Schools, 1996-2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cluster Group, 1999, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Coalition of the American Indian Chicago Community, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Jan Connor Research Project, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Degree Plan, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Evanston Native American Education Committee, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Ann French, 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Federation of Independent Illinois College and Universities, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - File Folder Inventories, 1991-1998 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Fort Peck Holdings, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Fundraising/Scholarship 2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Grade change/add-drop sheets, blank, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Health Care, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Illinois Articulation, Initiative IAI, 1994-1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Illinois Higher Education Master Plan, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Illinois Virtual Campus, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Indian Community Employee survey, 1984-1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Indian Education Act: Parent Committee Manual, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Inter Office Memorandums, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Library Index System, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Madison Technical College, job postings, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Margrette University Archives, 1995-2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mascotts, Memos on the use of Indian Mascotts, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - McNickle Center, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Menominee Community Center of Chicago, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Morning Star Foundation, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Minnesota Historical Society, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Minnesota Indian List Serve, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Mitchell Indian Museum, 1993-2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - NAES College, Twin Cities Campus, General Information, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - NAFPA, foster parents, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - NAPT, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Natawn Scholarship, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - National Archives, guide, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - National Archives, Great Lakes Region, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Off the Wall, news clippings, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Office of Academic Affairs, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - 125 Oneida, 92 Ojibwa 123, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Orientation meeting, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Public Policy Program at NAES College, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Policy Statement (Sexual Harassment), undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Research Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Self study, 1995-2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Self study, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Site Council, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Streetwise, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Spring Quarter Report, May 2001, Summer Institute, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Student ID’s, blank, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Strategies Plan, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Time Sheets, blank, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Urban Natives of Chicago Youth Council, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Martinez, 2000-2002 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Women’s leadership development, Fall 1993 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - YMCA, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Series III: Course Planning Materials
  - HL 200 Alcohol and its Effects on American Indian Communities, instructor, Joe White Eyes, course outline, Spring 1987 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - HT 480 Contemporary Issues in National, History of American Historical Perspectives, instructor, David Beck, syllabus, Spring 1994 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - CS 426 Cultural Preservation, Spring 1996 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - CS 410/411, Dynamics of Business, Instructor, Mike Cervantes, syllabus, Fall 1997 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - CS 410, Dynamics of Community Health, Instructor, Shangreaux, Spring 1993 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - CS 410, Dynamics of Community Health, Instructor, Shangreaux, Spring 1993 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - CS 410, Dynamics of Community Health, Instructor, Shangreaux, Spring 1993 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - CS 410, Dynamics of Community Health, Instructor, Shangreaux, Spring 1993 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - CS 425 Dynamics of Cultural Resource Management and Projects, CS 436 "Core," instructor, Geri Shangreaux, Spring 1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - CS 460 Dynamics of Government and Law/CS461 Child and Family Law, instructor, Beck/La Pier, Spring 1993 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - CS 460 Dynamics of Government and Law, Instructor, Rosalyn La Pier, syllabus, Spring 1994 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - CS 450 Dynamics of History and Culture, instructor, Lola Hill, Spring 1992 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - CS 440 Dynamic and History and Project, Instructors, Shangreaux and Evans, Spring 1995 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - CS 440 Dynamic of History and Project, Instructors, Shangreaux and Evans, Spring 1996 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - CS 415/6 Dynamics of Human Services, Instructors, Shangreaux, syllabus, Spring 1994 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - CS 455 Dynamics of Indian Philosophy and World View, Instructors, Wesley L. Andrews, course description, May, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - CS 440 Dynamics of Language ad Learning, Instructor, Hill, Fall 1991 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - CS 441 Dynamics and Language and Learning, instructors, Terry Strauss and Tim Vermillion, Fall 1988 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - CS 440 Dynamics and Language and Learning, instructor, Lola Hill, Spring 1993 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - CS 440 Dynamics and Language and Learning, instructors, Terry Strauss and Wesley L. Andrews, rough syllabus, Fall 1989 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - CS 441 Dynamics of Language and Learning, instructor, Terry Straus, Fall 1987 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - CS 445 Dynamics of Literature, CS 446 Literature Project, instructors, Rudnick and Turner, Fall 1995 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - CS 425/426 Dynamics of Philosophy and Worldview, core, Spring 1998 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - CS 451 History of Indians of the Upper Midwest, course list, instructor, Beck, Spring 1983 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - CS 455 Indian Philosophy and World View, CS 456, instructor, syllabus, Summer 1991 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Introduction to Alcoholism, (Through Montay College), Fall 1989 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - CS 420 Introduction to Environmental Law: Clean Water, instructor, Ellen Carpenter, syllabus, Fall 1995 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Instruction for preparing a syllabus, Fall, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - CS 445 Language and Literature, instructor, Lola Hill, syllabus, Spring 1991 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - CS 420 Public Policy, Dynamics "core," instructors, Roslyn Lapier and Marney Stately (Twin Cities), research for class, Fall 1992 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - CS 420 Public Policy, Dynamics "core," instructors, Roslyn Lapier and Marney Stately (Twin Cities), research for class, Fall 1992 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Role of City Government, instructors, Terry Straus and Yvonne Murray, Spring 1994 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Schedule of courses and programs, 1989-2000 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Schedule of courses and programs, 1989-2000 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Social Science Methods, 1994-1999 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - CS 490/491, Special topics Seminar-Columbus, the Indians and Human Progress, instructors, Straus, Minnie Two Shoes, syllabus, Fall ‘91 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Materials related to Conferences, Meetings, and Festivals
  - AAC meeting, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - AAC meeting, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - AAC meeting, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - AAC meeting, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - AAC meeting, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - AAC meeting, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - AAC meeting, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - AAC meeting, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - AAC meeting, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - AAC meeting, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Children’s Museum Program, Festival, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Dean’s Meeting, 1999-2000 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Dean’s Meeting, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Dean’s Meeting, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Faculty Senate, Nov 1996 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Senate, Nov 1998 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Senate, Oct 1998 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Senate, June 1999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Senate, Oct 1999 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Senate, Oct 1999 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Keshena, Oct 1997 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - NAES College Workshop, POW-WOW Materials, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - NASP-UIC, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Policy Breakfast, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Public Policy, Faculty Meeting, June 2000 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Staff meeting, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Tribal leaders, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Series V: Bibliographies
  - Health Bibliographies, 1992-1997 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Health Printouts LOC, Bibliographies undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - History, Indians of Upper Midwest, Bibliographies 1993 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Indian Child Welfare Act, Text of the Indian Child Welfare Act, Bibliographies 1901 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Indian Woman, Bibliographies 1982-1992 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Journals in the NAES College Library, Bibliographies, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Jurisdiction and Sovereignty, Bibliography, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Library of Congress, bibliographic print out, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - McNickle, Bibliography, 1990Menominee, Primary Sources, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Menominee Primary Sources, Missions, American Indians, Bibliography, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Collecting Material Culture: Race and Representations of Native Americans, Museums, Bibliography, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - National Archives materials, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Native American Woman, bibliography, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Psychology Literature, American Indian General, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Stephen Riggs, Bibliography, undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Substance Abuse, Pregnancy and the Law, bibliography, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Stereotypes, bibliography, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Sol Tax, biography, bibliography, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Urban Indian Projects, LOC, bibliography, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Essays
  - Armin Beck, "Self-Definition and Community Development," 1978 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Joel Beck, "Creating Leadership," 1998 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Ellen Carpenter, "Issues Paper: An Introduction to Federal Indian Environmental Law," 1995 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Thomas W. Cougar, "The Crossroads," 1996 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Robert V. Dumont, "Notes on Community Service for Native American Communities," undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - D’Arcy McNickle, excerpt from The Surrounded, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Series VII: Grant Materials
  - Title IX Evaluation, 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Title IX, Denver, 1996-1998 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Title IX, Denver, 1996-1998 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Series VIII: Restricted
  - Resumes and contracts, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Resumes, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Professional evaluation, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Evaluation, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 14)